Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/chris-applegate-67220a6 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Non-profits
Investment Management
Strategic Planning

Certifications

Practical Project Management
LEED Credentialing Maintenance
Mortgage Action Alliance Member
Master Certified Mortgage Banker

Chris Applegate

Partner at Higher Education Innovation Group, LL Arlington, Virginia, United States

Summary

Chris Applegate has served in numerous regional and statewide initiatives for NOVA during the last 5 years regarding fiscal control and expansion of Green Energy Industry and Information Assurance Curricula. Chris is State Chair of Virginia's Weatherization Training & Assistance Advisory Program; also serves as State Chair of Virginia's Energy Workforce Consortium, and a County Board appointed Advisory Board member to implement the 40 year Community Energy Plan (CEP). Chris has developed relationships with the German Embassy regarding education and international trade with Virginia.

Chris started his 38 year career with the Board of Governors, Federal Reserve System becoming an Operations Chief in charge of the Money Supply Index and Strategic Planning. He has held many re-engineering roles in banking & technology from Section Chief, Chief Information Officer, Vice President, President, Chief Financial Officer, and Board Member(s). Chris also Chaired the Mortgage Bankers Association School of Mortgage Banking and is the owner of a mortgage company. One of his proudest professional achievements was being nominated by President Bill Clinton to be his Assistant Secretary of the Treasury. Chris is an adjunct graduate professor of Finance, Accounting, Quantitative Theory, Strategic Planning, and Leadership.

Chris is graduated from the George Washington University with a BBA in Economics and an MBA in Accounting. He is also a Master Certified Mortgage Banker, MBA School of Mortgage Banking and licensed through the federal National Mortgage Licensing Registry. Chris is also experienced as a Non-Profit Investment & Financial Officer.

Specialties: Certified Mortgage Banker, Mortgage Banking Association, MBA-Accounting, GWU; Higher Education Workforce initiatives.

Experience

Higher Education Innovation Group, LLC Partner
February 2018 - Present (5 years 7 months)
Washington D.C. Metro Area

Commonwealth United Mortgage Company CEO/ Chief Financial Officer/International Consultant April 1987 - Present (36 years 5 months) Arlington, Virginia

Overseas Asia assignment for DoD Financial Management. Intuitive, innovative, confident, and entrepreneurial executive with a distinguished 45+year career reflecting an outstanding record of leadership performance and achievements in delivering strong market, financial, IT, and operational results. Track record in turning around underperforming organizations into top producers, improving financial outcomes, strengthening budgeting and productivity while reducing costs via long-term project planning, information system mission planning, generating new business, effectively delegating, and improving employee morale. Exceptional communicator with an extensive network of contacts and successes in building strong relationships with leaders in politics, business, and professional sports – e.g., Federal/State agencies, U.S. Senate and House, Prime Ministers, Secretaries of State, World Bank, lobbyists, Embassy/Ambassadors, and NFL players. Highly adept at conceptualizing solutions to problems using best practices and creativity. Maintain the highest of integrity standards.

Commonwealth United, Inc.
President
April 1987 - Present (36 years 5 months)

Northern Virginia Community College 5 years 11 months

State Chairman: Energy Workforce Consortium State Resources January 2011 - June 2013 (2 years 6 months)

Workforce Planning for the Energy Industry.

State Chairman: Weatherization Assistance Program 2011 - June 2013 (2 years)

Energy Plan development.

County Board Appointment: Community Energy Plan Implementation Advisory Board Member 2011 - June 2013 (2 years)

Director-Arlington Center August 2007 - June 2013 (5 years 11 months)

Director

August 2007 - June 2013 (5 years 11 months) Arlington, Virginia

Developed Cyber Security curriculum strategy.

Director

August 2007 - June 2013 (5 years 11 months) Arlington, Virginia

Developed Transatlantic Vocational Training model for the German Embassy in support of German companies locating in the U.S.

Arlington-Alexandria Workforce Investment Board Board Member 2007 - June 2013 (6 years) Arlington, VA.

City of Alexandria Commissioner- Employment 2007 - June 2013 (6 years) Alexandria, VA.

Colombo Bank
Executive Vice President & Board Member
2005 - 2006 (1 year)
Rockville, MD.

Potomac Bank Senior Vice President 2003 - 2004 (1 year) Fairfax, VA.

Lending Operations

F&M National Bank, NA, Mortgage Subsidiary President, Chief Financial Officer, Managing Director 1998 - 2002 (4 years)

Frederick, MD.

Trustbank, FSB Chief Technology Officer & Senior Vice President 1984 - 1987 (3 years) Vienna, VA.

Board of Governors, Federal Reserve System Section Chief Administrator & Strategic Planner 1973 - 1984 (11 years)

Washington, D.C.

Education

MBA School of Mortgage Banking
MCMB, Real Estate Finance · (2000 - 2001)

The George Washington University - School of Business Master of Business Administration (M.B.A.), Accounting & Finance · (1976 - 1978)

The George Washington University - School of Business
Bachelor's Degree, Econometrics and Quantitative Economics · (1971 - 1974)